<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A letter to a friend, in vindication of the proceedings against Sir John Fenwick, by Bill of Attainder, with some remarks on his printed paper</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 67KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 20 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A48174</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12387096</idno>
  <idno type="VID">60872</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240951515</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing L1653</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R11182</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">12387096</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A48174)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 60872)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 766:14)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A letter to a friend, in vindication of the proceedings against Sir John Fenwick, by Bill of Attainder, with some remarks on his printed paper</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 28 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Samuel Heyrick ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1697.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="personal_name">Fenwick, John, --  Sir, 1645?-1697.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Bill of attainder --  England.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-05 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-10 </date>
            <label>Kate Allen </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-10 </date>
            <label>Kate Allen</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:60872:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:60872:1"/>
            <p>A LETTER TO A FRIEND, IN VINDICATION of the PROCEEDINGS AGAINST Sir JOHN FENWICK, BY <hi>Bill of Attainder.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>With some Remarks on his Printed Paper.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Samuel Heyrick,</hi> at <hi>Grayes-Inn-Gate</hi> in <hi>Holborn.</hi> MDCXCVII.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="half_title">
            <pb facs="tcp:60872:2"/>
            <p>A LETTER TO A FRIEND, In Vindication of the Proceedings against Sir <hi>John Fenwick,</hi> by Bill of Attainder.</p>
            <p>With some Remarks on his Printed Paper.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:60872:3"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:60872:3"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:60872:4"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:60872:4"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> Was never a very great Friend to <hi>Apologies;</hi> yet I find it necessary, at this Time, to make use of them. I do it for the satisfaction of such who may ask, <hi>why this Paper came out no sooner?</hi> and, <hi>why, after such a Delay, it came out at all?</hi> seeing the Business of it, as they conceive, is blown over, and the Town has fresh Subjects to talk of.</p>
            <p>For the <hi>First,</hi> the <hi>Delay;</hi> a desire of seeing some Memorials not to be immediately had, and of discoursing with some Persons not every day to be met with; a great deal of other Business, and an expectation of something of this Nature from other hands; as they are true Suggestions, so, I presume, they make up a just Excuse.</p>
            <p>Concerning the <hi>Second,</hi> the <hi>Unseasonableness</hi> of this Account, I take the confidence to say that it seems to me to be a very great Mistake. For there is a <hi>Party,</hi> (who know better what they are <hi>against,</hi> then what they are <hi>for</hi>) whose Heat, tho' very violent, is yet perpetual. This is evident to all who are either so curious as to enquire after the <hi>Papers</hi> they Spread abroad, or so unhappy as to engage with them in <hi>Discourse.</hi> The Matter is by no Means over with this sort of Men: The <hi>Bill of Attainder</hi> is their daily Subject. They are Transport<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb facs="tcp:60872:5"/> with so great a rage against it, that for the sake of it, they declaim against all <hi>Acts of Attainder.</hi> Tho' the Memory of Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> is not, upon other accounts, much valued by them; yet, in <hi>this Point</hi> they represent it as the Glory of her Reign, that no <hi>Act of Attainder</hi> passed in it. I am not going about to justify all such <hi>Acts,</hi> or to plead for the <hi>frequency</hi> of them. But I would, upon this occasion, observe to the Men of this Faction, that Queen <hi>Eliza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth</hi> did pass such <hi>Acts;</hi> and that the last, which the late <hi>King James</hi> passed, was very far from the Reasonableness and Justice either of those in <hi>Her</hi> Time, or of this in King <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam</hi>'s.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act of</hi> Irel. 11 Eliz. <hi>c.</hi> 3. 13 Eliz. <hi>c.</hi> 5, 7. 27 Eliz. <hi>c.</hi> 1. 28 Eliz. <hi>c.</hi> 7, 8.</note> Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> did, <hi>in Ireland,</hi> pass many <hi>Acts of Attainder;</hi> and, in some of them, great Numbers of Persons were included. And I cannot but take notice, that in the last <hi>Act,</hi> here cited, for the <hi>Attainder</hi> of <hi>John Brown</hi> of <hi>Knockmontin, and very many others;</hi> (I think in some of the rest too) the Stile runs thus: <q rend="margQuotes">It may please Your High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness for the <hi>good preservation</hi> of Your most Excellent Maiesty's <hi>Government,</hi> and of the good <hi>Peace, Unity,</hi> and <hi>Rest</hi> of <hi>all Us</hi> Your most bounden and obedient <hi>Subjects</hi> thereof, the Lords Spiritual and Temporal, and the Commons in this Parliament Assembled, that it may be enacted by the Authority of this present Parliament, that the said <hi>John Brown, John Bradah, &amp;c.</hi> be, and shall be, by the Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of this present Act, <hi>Convicted</hi> and <hi>Attainted</hi> of <hi>High-Treason.</hi>
               </q> So that, in the Judgment of those Times, such an <hi>Act</hi> was not reckoned, Inhumane and Unmerciful, and of very ill Consequence to the Publick; but, a present Means to the
<pb facs="tcp:60872:5"/> Common Good. That <hi>Excellent Queen, who was always the same,</hi> could not look upon an <hi>Act of Attainder,</hi> as <hi>mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciful</hi> in one Country and <hi>unmerciful</hi> in another.</p>
            <p>The late King <hi>James,</hi> by an <hi>Act</hi> of a pretended Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, assembled at <hi>Dublin, May</hi> the 7th, <hi>1689,</hi> Attainted of High-Treason, above <hi>Two Thousand Four Hundred,</hi> of the Nobility, Gentry, Clergy, and Commonalty of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Ireland</hi> (amongst whom as there were several Women and Children, so there were some Great Persons, now sitting here in the House of Lords, <hi>viz. James</hi> Duke of <hi>Ormond, Robert Boyle</hi> Earl of <hi>Cork, John</hi> Earl of <hi>Mulgrave</hi>); the List of whose mere Names fill no less than Thirty Pages in <hi>Quarto,</hi> close printed in Columns. Where now is the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partiality of those Men, who will not suffer one hard Word to fall, which may censure King <hi>James</hi>'s Act: whilst with all Bitterness they arraign this of King <hi>William?</hi> Yet in <hi>This</hi> the Legislative Power found it necessary (at least in one Instance) to exert it self; that Conspirators might not for the <hi>future,</hi> learn a Method of escaping from Justice, by <hi>taking off a Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Witness,</hi> by Bribery, Poyson, or other evil Means. The Consequence of such Encouragement would be, the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dangering of our Religion and Property, and the bringing us to <hi>Wooden Shoes,</hi> and <hi>Deities,</hi> of a like Insensible Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance. To me it is manifest, that the <hi>Legislative Power</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded upon the truest, and noblest Principles; I mean those of <hi>Justice</hi> to the Person and <hi>Charity</hi> to the Publick. These are founded on true, unbiass'd, and (as I may call it) <hi>dry Reason;</hi> which is the Soul of Law: whereas the Pity which would save from Punishment such particular Persons as are
<pb facs="tcp:60872:6"/> Enemies to the Kingdom, and rather justify then acknowledg their Crimes, proceeds from a Judgment so <hi>macerated in Bodily Passion</hi> (as a great Man speaks) that it is both un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manly and mischeivous. The Mercy of such a Passion is cruel. It says, in effect, to the Chirurgion, <hi>You Bloody and Barbarous Man, will you be so unmerciful as to cut off the Gangreen'd Arm? Rather then be so Inhu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane to it, let the Body perish.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I hope, that notwithstanding the Clamour of Men, trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported with the Heat of Popish Zeal; the <hi>Legislative Power</hi> will always prefer the publick before the private Good: And the Character of this <hi>Reign</hi> will be <hi>true Clemency;</hi> which is on one side fenced against <hi>Rigour,</hi> and against <hi>Remisness,</hi> on the other.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:60872:6"/>
            <head>
               <hi>A LETTER</hi> Concerning the Attainder and Execution of Sir <hi>JOHN FENWICK.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I do not wonder to find you concerned to know upon what grounds the <hi>Act of Attainder</hi> was lately carried. The De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bates were long, and the contradiction was great. Every thing that is unusual, and that in the first appearances, seems a strain upon Justice as well as Law, needs a Commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary. A short prejudice does sometimes seize one so strongly, that a long Discourse will be necessary to settle his judgment aright: and therefore I shall endeavour to give you as full an account of that whole matter as I have been able to collect, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther from what I learned from the <hi>Bar of both Houses</hi> when all were permitted to come in, or from discourse in Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sation afterwards; which, I hope, will serve, without any ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions or observations of my own, to help you to see this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in a clear light, and to take off from your self or others, any Impressions that flying Reports or some short Papers may have made. It has been the more easie for me to procure you such an Authentical Relation of that matter as will satisfie you, because <hi>both Houses of Parliament</hi> did, upon this occasion, slacken their otherwise necessary Rules of having all their <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bates</hi>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:60872:7"/> with shut Doors, and only among themselves. They seemed in that to comply with the Methods of the Justice of this Kingdom; in which <hi>Judges</hi> argue and give their Opinions in <hi>Open Courts,</hi> and in the hearing of all: So, since they brought a Gentleman to a Tryal, they not only heard <hi>Councel</hi> and <hi>Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesses</hi> with open doors; but, in most of their deliberations, they acted like a <hi>Judicature</hi> that was neither afraid nor asha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to own what they did. But, to bring those Debates, of which I was so lucky as to hear a great deal, under some Form, I shall lead you, as they proceeded, by these steps.</p>
            <p n="1">1. I shall show you on what reason they proceeded by Bill in this Case.</p>
            <p n="2">2. On what reason they went out of the Common forms of Law in Inferior Courts, in some steps that they made.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Upon what grounds it was that they judged this Unfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunate Gentleman Guilty: and then,</p>
            <p n="4">4. I shall acquaint you with some passages before and at his Execution.</p>
            <p>In stating these matters to you, I shall comply faithfully with your desire of knowing what was said of both sides, for, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst every step that was made: as far as I was able to collect from what was said.</p>
            <p>It was in general objected that there were Laws, and Courts of Law where Offenders were to be tryed.</p>
            <p>It was thought a thing of dangerous consequence to proceed against any by Bill, which might have fatal effects, even to the subversion of the Laws of the Kingdoms; which (if in any thing) ought to be observed most sacredly in what relates to the Lives of the Subjects.</p>
            <p>It was said, that Factions might prevail in Parliament as well as elsewhere, and what was done at one time would be made a Rule or Precedent to warrant the like at another time.</p>
            <p>It was alledged, that Subjects knew the Laws, and how to govern themselves by them, or when they must fall under them; but no Man could know what a Parliament might call or make a crime, and so no man could be safe.</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:60872:7"/>
            <p>It was yet more necessary that this should be certain in Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses of Treason, where the Punishment went not only to life, but to the corrupting the Blood.</p>
            <p>By the great Statute of <hi>Edward</hi> III. the Overt Act must be proved. By that of <hi>Edward</hi> VI. there must be two Witnesses brought face to face: and all these securities were of late re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inforced by the <hi>New Act of Tryals in Cases of High Treason;</hi> but all these would signifie nothing, if this Method were taken of attainting men by a Law. This was inforced with a variety of Topicks, as you see the Subjects can well bear them.</p>
            <p>But in opposition to all this, it was said, that the Parliament had often proceeded in this method. Very many Precedents were cited of Ancient times; some of these were indeed after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards condemned, but so were also the Proceedings at Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Law: for partial Juries and corrupt Judges are plagues that have visited us but too often. Therefore it was no dero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation from Parliamentary Proceedings, to confess that in bad times they have been unjust and extreme.</p>
            <p>Still the Authority was kept up, as that which had been re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>served by the <hi>Proviso</hi> in the Statute of 25 of <hi>Edward</hi> III. and though that <hi>Proviso</hi> had not been made, the Nature of this Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of ours in <hi>England</hi> makes it.</p>
            <p>It was indeed seldom to be made use of; but when enormous crimes broke out, against which no Provision had been made, Then a Law, as they thought, might declare the Nature of such crimes and apply a proportioned Punishment to them; so in King <hi>Henry</hi> VIII. time, when a Pot full of Pottage was poisoned in the Bishop of <hi>Rochester</hi>'s Kitchen, of which some eating of it had died; poisoning was declared by an Act to be High-Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son, and the Punishment of it was to be boiled alive, and the Cook suffered by that Law; which was never censured by any.</p>
            <p>When the Nun of <hi>Kent</hi> pretended to Visions, that revealed to her the unlawfulness of that King's purpose of Divorce and of a second Marriage, and that if he did go on to it, he should dye a Villains Death; the Parliament adjudged this to be the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:60872:8"/> Crime of Treason against the King's Life and Crown, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned some to be attainted of Treason, and others of Mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prision, for the share they had in it. This Sir <hi>Thomas Moore</hi> justified.</p>
            <p>It is true, Attainders grew to be much in use during the rest of that Reign which was much and justly censured. These things ought not to come too often; the crimes ought to be enormous, and the Evidence ought to be so full that no doubt can remain of it: Many were then attainted upon Depositions produced with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out bringing the Witnesses themselves to be examined; the crimes objected were slight matters, some passionate words, some Coats of Arms, some pieces of Embroidery, as in the Case of the Countess of <hi>Salisbury</hi> and the D. of <hi>Norfolk;</hi> but the chief injustice of all was that Prisoners were attainted without being brought to answer for themselves, or to object to the Evidence laid against them. A Parliament was certainly under the eternal Laws of Justice, and therefore it was an injustice never to be excused not to admit men to speak for themselves. One Attain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der past in <hi>Edward</hi> VI. Reign, when tho' the party was not heard, the Witnesses were heard; but when the D. of <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merset</hi> came to be Tryed both for Treason and Felony, he had not the benefit of the Accusers being brought face to face, but was proceeded against upon Depositions read in the Court; he was acquitted for the Treason but cast for Felony, and that occasio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the Act which the Commons Grafted upon a Bill sent down by the Lords in the subsequent Session.</p>
            <p>In Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi>'s long Reign there was indeed no Attainder, but there was a very extraordinary proceeding supported by a Parliamentary Authority in a famous tho' invidious Case; and if a Parliament may supersede any of the common Forms of Law they may carry that as far as they see good cause.</p>
            <p>In Kings <hi>James</hi>'s time those who had been concerned in the Gun-Powder-Treason were by Act of Parliament attainted after they were dead, which was plainly against Law; for when a Man dies, by our Law all his crimes dye with him.</p>
            <p>In King <hi>Charles</hi> the First time the much talked of Attainder of
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:60872:8"/> the Earl of <hi>Strafford</hi> has been generally ill represented; he was attainted upon the Evidence of one Witness, who deposed that he had offered an advice to the King to bring in a Forreign Force to subdue the Kingdom; whereas all the other Witnesses said that by this Kingdom they meant no other but the Kingdom of <hi>Scotland</hi> then in Rebellion, no discourse being of <hi>England;</hi> so whether he said <hi>this</hi> Kingdom or not they could not say, but they understand it all to relate to <hi>Scotland.</hi> Now since the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lative <hi>this,</hi> tho' in general it belongs to the place where one is, yet may well belong to that which was the subject of the dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course, tho' this Kingdom in general is certainly this Kingdom, yet these words <hi>this Kingdom</hi> may be understood of that King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of which they were speaking. The Execrableness of that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding was the attainting a man upon a single Evidence when the sense of them was so doubtful, or rather on the contrary when it was so certain that those words were to be understood in another sense. It was therefore the injustice of the procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding that is here to be accused, and not the proceeding by Bill. For it is hard to tell what any Parliament would do, or rather what it would not do against a Minister who upon their refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing to give all the supplies that were asked, should tell a King that he was absolved from all the Rules of Government, and might bring in a Forreign Army to subdue his People.</p>
            <p>In King <hi>Charles</hi> II. time, some of the chief Regicides were at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainted after their deaths and their bodies were raised and expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed to infamy, tho' no Law could reach that.</p>
            <p>And in King <hi>James</hi> II. time, the D. of <hi>Monmouth</hi> was attain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in absence without assigning him a day to come in, and that upon a Slender proof. By this, not to run backward to ancien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Precedents, it is clear that Parliaments are in the constant practise of Bills of Attainder.</p>
            <p>But to justifie such a way of proceeding two things are ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessary. 1. The Crime ought to be of a high nature in it self; who will say but a Conspiracy to blow up the House of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, to blow up the Magazins in the Tower, or to burn the Fleet of <hi>England,</hi> tho' in themselves but misdemeanors, may
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:60872:9"/> be raised by a Parliamentary authority to be Crimes of a higher nature and so be punished accordingly, as poisoning was from being but Felony declared to be high Treason. 2. Another thing is that the Evidence must be certain, so certain that none can doubt of it. When these two are observed no injustice can be done; and certainly tho' forms are necessary for all the Infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour Courts of Justice, yet the Supreme Authority is above them, and is under no other rules but the rules of Justice and Equity.</p>
            <p>This Government has a peculiar felicity belonging to it, that it admits of no Torture; every one will acknowledge that it is a felicity, and it is so peculiar to us that no Government now in the World, the freest not excepted, has shut it out, but this only. But to ballance this when Cases happen of great consequence, and notoriously evident, in which all the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary forms of Law cannot be observed, the legislative Authority may and must interpose, otherwise the Publick might be endan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gered by too scrupulous an adhering to forms.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Romans</hi> who of all Nations both understood Liberty the best, and liked it the most, reckoned that sort of Justice was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed never to be departed from; but their Laws might be su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perseded; sometimes they put all in the power of the Consuls with a <hi>viderint Consules,</hi> &amp;c. when the danger was more ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treme a Dictator was made in whose breast all the Laws were lodged. In great Cases the People judged and sometimes in a very summary way with great regard to Justice, but little to Law, when it seemed to stand in the way of Justice: And yet in all the time of liberty, there were not above three condemned for affecting to make themselves Masters of their Liberties.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Portian</hi> Law had secured all the <hi>Roman</hi> Citizens from Capital Punishments, yet a few years after it had passed, a whole legion having perfidiously f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>llen in upon <hi>Rhegium,</hi> the <hi>Romans</hi> without regard to that Law put them all to death, such regard had they to Justice.</p>
            <p>In all free Governments, there are extraordinary methods for extreme Cases, and tho' Courts are justly put under Rules yet that superiour authority is above all. Such were the <hi>D cta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors</hi>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:60872:9"/> at <hi>Rome,</hi> such are the <hi>Inquisitors</hi> at <hi>Venice</hi> (not the Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siastical but Civil Inquisitors) such are the Chambers of Justice among the <hi>Grisons,</hi> and among all out of <hi>England</hi> upon a cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dible tho but single Evidence Torture is made use of.</p>
            <p>In <hi>England</hi> Tryals of Treason went at first at large by the Common Law, till the Statute of <hi>Edward</hi> III. hath both limi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the Crimes and the Evidence. This had still a reserve in it for a Parliamentary proceeding, which amounts to this, that as to Evidence, Parliaments may proceed as Juries do in case of Felony to cast the Party upon a single Evidence with strong Presumptions, and that as to the Nature of Crimes such actions as do in their own nature tend to the destruction of the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, tho' not enumerated in that act, may by them be decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to be High Treason. There is no occasion for this in the present case; that is, for declaring it by any new Act to be Treason; The inviting of a French Army into <hi>England</hi> being certainly High Treason.</p>
            <p>As for its being a Precedent, it is, only a Precedent to a Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentary proceeding. When any Parliament has a mind to proceed in this way, they have already Precedents enough: A new one after so many does not make the matter much stronger. If they had none at all, their supreme power sets them above all forms and rules except that of real Justice. They must take care of the publick, and secure it from danger. They must not put an innocent man to death upon no account whatsoever, that were murther in them. The greater their power is the more careful they ought to be in the use and application of it. <hi>England</hi> is safe while in the hands of a Parliament. They are in their own hands, in the hands of their Representatives. But if ever the Nation is so unhappy as to make a very bad choice, it must perish, whether a body so ill composed had Precedents or had them not for what they were about to do. This great Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority must be applyed with great care and caution. The na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the fact must be enormous, and highly so (as has been before observed) otherwise it does not deserve their regard, even tho' it might be very criminal: And what can be more
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:60872:10"/> enormous than to treat and send Messages to invite over a <hi>French</hi> Army? It were invidious as well as it is needless to aggravate this which carries in it all the miseries imaginable that can hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen to a Nation, and that from our being the happiest would soon render us the miserablest Nation upon Earth. We have all seen during the progress of the War, a Body of unnatural men among us that were visibly favouring our Enemies in instances that have been too publick and scandalous to need to be insisted on. To these we may justly impute both the length of the War, and the dangers we have been in, of being twice sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prized by Forreign Invasion from <hi>La Hogue</hi> and <hi>Dunkirk.</hi> To this all the dangers the King's Person has been in of Assassinations may be also ascribed; and with respect be it said, the assassina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the Kingdom, to which the other was to make way, was much the blacker Crime. Confusions among our selves, tho' they may throw us into great Convulsions, in which our Kings may have a very dismal share, as happened in the late Wars, yet they may have their <hi>Crisis.</hi> The Nation came again to it self in the year 1660. and all things returned to their former State. But a Forreign Conquest enslaves us and our Posterity for ever. And whereas it was said by the Councel for the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soner, that this Gentleman was not so considerable that the safety of the Government could be in danger by his means, and that therefore it was not necessary to proceed against him in so extraordinary a manner; which was urged in words not very decent, expressing a contempt of a man of Birth and Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity: But to this it was answered, that the Crime and not the man were to be considered. The inviting over a <hi>French</hi> Army was so heinous a thing, that on whomsoever it fell it must fall with all its weight. It must not pass over as a slight matter besides that; he at the Head of the 2000 Horse that were promised was not so inconsiderable. If such Invitation had encouraged the <hi>French</hi> to undertake the Invasion last year, that was so near proving so fatal to <hi>England,</hi> such a Crime being of the highest nature is very proper for the Supreme Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:60872:10"/> to proceed in; sure there may be defects in the Evidence, which the Courts of Law cannot and ought not to supply. And, as to the evidence, this ought to be laid down for a foundation, that it ought to be certain, such as no man doubts of, or can well make himself doubt of; for if there appears no more but a just suspicion af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the whole is taken altogether, certainly in that case the Prisoner ought to be acquitted. But if the Evidence comes so home, that if a Jury were to try one for Felony upon such proof, it cannot be supposed that they would go from the Bar, then, tho' there should be such de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects in it, that by the rules of Inferior Courts, and by the Law lately passed, a man could not be reached upon it; here would be a strange return to the Crown for passing such a Law, in which a particular Exception was made as to proceedings upon Impeachments, or other proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings in Parliament, if upon new and strange Emergents, and when we were so lately in such visible and imminent danger, the Parliament would not proceed according to that power, that was inherent in it, and had been ever reserved to it. They were to arrive at Justice whatsoever might lie in their way. Justice was still to be sacred: God forbid an innocent man should suffer; but he was a wise King as well as an inspired Writer, who had made the acquitting the Guilty, a Crime equally odious with the condemning the Innocent.</p>
            <p>Thus I have given you as fully as I could gather it, the summ of the Argument as to the matter in general. This was the finest part of the debate, and that of the most lasting use; here it was (as far as I could collect) that the much greatest part of those that liked not the Bill did stick: for besides the aversion that all men have for medling in Blood, many thought this might be made
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:60872:11"/> a common practice. They could not see how far it might go; and therefore thought it safer to let the Bill fall, then to revive, or, at least, fortifie that which might become very dangerous in its consequences. For I am apt to think they had no concern for <hi>Sir John Fenwick,</hi> and did not doubt of his guilt, only they had an aversion to the Precedent: And of those who argued for it, I know diverse, who had great ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derness for the matter, and much for <hi>Sir John</hi> in particular: But since they thought the thing just in it self, the circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stances of Affairs both at home and abroad, made them conclude it to be neeessary to pass a Bill of that nature when it was once moved; since the rejecting it would have given great Cause of Triumph to our Enemies, and must have very much disheartened our Friends and Allies. This was not to be considered, 'till the Justice of the point was first setled; for that would be, as if a man were to die, because it was expedient he should die: but if it appeared to be just, then the expediency of it had great weight as to the passing the Bill.</p>
            <p>The <hi>second</hi> Head of which I promised to give you an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, is the reasons, on which some steps were made out of the common Forms of Law. It was first in general urged, that here in a matter of Judicature the Commons assumed an equal share with the Lords; and more particularly, that they who could not so much as tender an Oath had yet jud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged a man Guilty of Treason, which seemed contrary to natural Equity. To this it was answered, it was certain that in the way of Judicature the Commons could only be the Accusers, and the Lords were the only Judges; but when they proceeded in the way of Legislation, both Houses must concur. This was the fate of all Bills of Attainders; some of these Bills were begun in the House of Commons. In <hi>Henry</hi> VIII. time, tho the Bills began in the House of
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:60872:11"/> Lords, yet several persons names were added by the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, which was the beginning of it as to those persons. That of the <hi>E. of Strafford</hi> was begun by the <hi>Commons,</hi> so was also the latest <hi>Precedent,</hi> that of the <hi>D. of Monmouth.</hi> It is true the Commons cannot tender an <hi>Oath,</hi> yet matters of Justice do oft pass upon a bare deposition where the Law do's not suffer an Oath to be tendred. So the acquittal in <hi>Tryals of Felony,</hi> and, till the late Act was past, in <hi>Tryals</hi> of <hi>Treason,</hi> was upon <hi>Depositions</hi> that could not be upon Oath: Yet they might be believed, and Juries must give their Verdicts upon them if they believe them; so the Commons believing the Depositions might upon these pass the Bill, tho no Oath could be tendred.</p>
            <p>Another step to which great exception was made, was the the reading of <hi>Goodman's Deposition.</hi> It was said this could not be admitted by Law. The Prisoner could not have the advantage of cross examining him, since he did not ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear face to face as is required by Law; nor was it proved that <hi>Sir John Fenwick,</hi> or any imployed by him, had any way persuaded <hi>Goodman</hi> to withdraw himself: It would be of very dangerous consequence if a man so accused should be condemned; for by this means a Witness, who, if pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced <hi>Viva voce</hi> to accuse a man, could not hurt him, being sound insufficient to convict him, yet should have more power to hurt him by his absence than if present.</p>
            <p>'To this it was Answered, that it was a known maxime, that the Practice of Parliament was the Law of Parliament: and the constant practice anciently had been to read <hi>Depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sitions.</hi> It is true, they were afterwards to consider of what importance such Depositions were, and what stress was to be laid on them; therefore there was Precedent enough for
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:60872:12"/> reading them, yet in Justice they ought to weigh every thing that could be offered to derogate from their credit: as they were to hear every thing that was offered to defame him or to lessen his credit. Might it not be urged as well against the Attainting men after they were dead, that they could not cross interrogate Witnesses, nor offer Proofs for their own justification. In such Cases there must indeed be such a fulness of proof, that it may appear that all exceptions are vain allegations, and no great weight was to be laid on such objections.</p>
            <p>Another step was the examining the Grand Jury<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, who had found the Bill against <hi>Sir John Fenwick,</hi> as to the Evidence, that <hi>Goodman</hi> had given before them against him. Those who had been of Mr. <hi>Cook's</hi> petty Jury were also examined as to the Evidence that <hi>Goodman</hi> gave in that Tryal. The <hi>Kings Council</hi> moved this, that by it, it might appear that <hi>Goodman</hi> had been always constant in his Evidence.</p>
            <p>But to this it was objected, that it was against Law: Those of the <hi>Grand Jury</hi> were under an Oath not to reveal the secrets that were before them; whatsoever was sworn be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore them was all to be examined over again in the Tryal; so, that could not be brought as part of the Evidence, and those who had tried another man were not to be brought as Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, as to what had passed in a Tryal to which <hi>Sir John Fenwick</hi> was not a party. It was also observed that those Jury-men varied in the report they gave of <hi>Goodman's Depositions.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But to all this it was answered, that Evidence might be
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:60872:12"/> brought to prove a presumption as well as to prove the main thing in issue. For since <hi>Goodman</hi> was gone, if any use was to be made of his Evidence, it was a strong pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sumption either for or against it, if it should appear that he was constant or, that he varied in it. The Parliament was now <hi>searching</hi> to find out truth: so every thing was to be followed that might help towards that. They were after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards to consider what use they might make of it; so tho' it might be against the Forms of Law, yet in the way in which they proceeded at present, it was very proper for them to examine into it. As for the <hi>Oath</hi> of <hi>the Grand Jury to keep the Evidence secret,</hi> it was an Oath in fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of the <hi>King;</hi> that so the Evidence might not be known to the Prisoner, till he should be brought to his Tryal. Since therefore this was an Oath to the King, they who were brought thither by his Council were freed from the obligation of it; and since this was indeed <hi>Sir John Fenwick</hi>'s <hi>Tryal,</hi> the end of the Oath was already Answe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, so that it did not bind them to conceal the Evidence that had been given before them.</p>
            <p>As for those who had been of <hi>Mr. Cook's Jury,</hi> their Oath was not to be Evidence against another Person; It was only a Circumstance that might direct them to judge what value they ought to set upon <hi>Goodman's</hi> De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>positions. As for the disagreement that might be among them, the Jury-men themselves, when first called in, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared they could not be positive in it as to particulars; because it was a good distance of time, and they had not sufficient notice to think and recollect. And as to the dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>agreement, it was not in the charge it self, nor the matter alledged against Sir <hi>John Fenwick,</hi> but it was only in some small circumstances, in which men might vary who had heard the Deposition but once; and so, are not like a
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:60872:13"/> Witness to a fact, that he has seen or known, which he is supposed to reflect oft upon; nor do they consider more upon such occasions, than whether the Evidence is so well made out, that they can give a general Verdict upon it.</p>
            <p>They therefore might misremember themselves as to some particulars which were of less consequence, that would undoubtedly be observed when it came to be debated how far <hi>Goodman's</hi> Evidence was to be made use of, or to be depended on; which was afterwards little insisted on, and seemed rather to be brought to shew the fairness of the proceeding in the whole matter, than to draw any Inferen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces from it to hurt the Prisoner.</p>
            <p>I come in the next place to tell you what the Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence was, upon which Sir <hi>John Fenwick</hi> was believed Guilty. I need not report Captain <hi>Porter</hi>'s Evidence, it being so oft in Print, as to this particular, both in Sir <hi>John Friend</hi>'s, in Sir <hi>William Parkin</hi>'s, and in <hi>Peter Cook</hi>'s Tryal. All that was special here was, that he said that the Lords left the rest of the Company about Five of the Clock, but he could not tell whither he went when he left the House, nor whether he went home that or some following Nights. All the People of the House where they dined were examined, who all deposed, that they were often coming to the Room where that Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany was, the Doors being all the while open; that they saw not <hi>Goodman</hi> there, nor had ever seen him there, as they remembred at any time; they believed he could not be there at that time. They also said that the Lords went away about Four of the Clock, and to that particular di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers other Witnesses were examined, who all agreed that
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:60872:13"/> it was about Four; so tho' some of these Witnesses were not much considered, yet that matter seemed to be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greed on, that they left the House about Four of the Clock; whereas <hi>Porter</hi> sware it was about Five. <hi>A Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord of Man-slaughter</hi> was also brought to lessen <hi>Porter</hi>'s credit; and whereas he said he could not tell when he went home, it was urged, that from thence it must be concluded he was drunk, and so could be no proper Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence to what past when he was in such a condition; some disagreement was also observed in the Printed Try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>als between the Evidence he gave as to <hi>Charnock</hi>'s com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to him after his return from <hi>France;</hi> in one it being that he came to him after his Confinement to <hi>Newgate,</hi> and the other after he was freed from his Confinement. This was much insisted on, and upon this it was said, that as he was the single Evidence, so he was a very doubtful one. To all this it was opposed, that by one unquestionable Evidence it appeared, that <hi>Goodman</hi> had once dined in the House with Sir <hi>John Friend,</hi> so he was known to the House; and by another it was proved that he had given direction to call for him that very day at that House, so little credit was due to the People of the House. As for the hour of their parting, when the days are so long as in <hi>May,</hi> no man can be positive to an hour except some circumstances oblige him to attend to it. A man may think it is <hi>Five,</hi> when it is but <hi>Four;</hi> time seemed to move quicker or slower as People were in hast or weary; so no stress could be laid on that. It is but an Inference that he was Drunk, because he did not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member when he went to his Lodgings; other considera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions besides that might make a man, who was too much a libertine, not be able to give an account of himself. The record of Man-slaughter did not at all af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect his fame or credit in what he Deposed upon Oath.</p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:60872:14"/>
            <p>The varying in the Tryals was occasioned by the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference between the <hi>Short-hand-writers,</hi> one had Writ all the Depositions one way, another had varyed in some. The Witnesses had complained to my <hi>Lord Chief Justice,</hi> after the <hi>Tryals</hi> came out, that their Depositions had been wrong taken; one of the <hi>Short-hand-writers</hi> was not placed so advantageously as the other; besides that the mark in <hi>Short-hand-writing</hi> that distinguishes between these two <hi>after he was confined,</hi> or <hi>after his confinement was over</hi> was so inconsiderable, that the exactest Writer might mistake; so the insisting so long on this was much wondred at.</p>
            <p>Upon the whole matter it was said, that though a bad man was at first a doubtful Witness, yet after so many Tryals, so great a canvassing to find matter to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject against him, and that not one point he had sworn was ever disproved, or so much as denied, by any who had died upon his Evidence; all this confirmed his credit beyond the possibility of calling it in que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stion.</p>
            <p>They who had suffered, had studied to cover the Late King all they could, and denied that they had seen any Commission from him for Assassinating the King; but in this they did not contradict Mr. <hi>Porter,</hi> he spoke not a word of a <hi>Commission to assassinate the King,</hi> but only of a <hi>Commission to attack and seize his Person,</hi> which none of them denied.</p>
            <p>If in any circumstances he had sworn wrong, they to discredit him, and to save their Friends, could not have omit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to deny and contradict it. This not one of them has done; Sir <hi>J. Friend</hi> and Sir <hi>W. Parkins</hi> had this very matter
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:60872:14"/> objected to them, it was a part of the Evidence against them, yet they died without denying it; which is not possible to sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose they would or could have done, if it had been False; since it would have discredited the Evidence, and so have been a means to save their Friends. This is the nature of a violent Presumption, which really goes further, to satisfy a Man's Mind, than ten Witnesses; for one may suspect them all how full or home soever they may swear: but this forces it self so upon a Man, that it determines his Assent, he believes it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause he cannot doubt of it; and therefore they concluded that Capt. <hi>Porter</hi> was not a doubtful Witness, but an undoubted one, since his Evidence was fortified with so many violent Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sumptions as every one of the dying Men had given to it; but most particularly by what <hi>Friend</hi> and <hi>Parkyns</hi> had said, who justified themselves in what they had done, but denied no part of that which was objected to them. This is more than any Jury in Cases of Felony would require to determine them to bring in their Verdict, and so must be enough to determine the Houses of Parliament.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Goodman</hi>'s Evidence was not much insisted on. It was pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved that he had been a common High-way-man; a Record was brought of designing to murder two of the Dutchess of <hi>Cleveland</hi>'s Sons; besides most horrid Blasphemies, that could scarce be heard with Patience. It was not proved that any in Sir <hi>John Fenwick</hi>'s Name had practised with him to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw, so it might be presumed that Horror for his false swear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing might have been his Motive. To all this it was said, that tho it appeared that he was a very wicked Man; yet since these Persons, as it was proved, had kept him Company much, they made him a more creditable Witness against them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves, than he could be against any other Person. The con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curring Circumstances in this Matter gave Credit to his Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stimony; for as to Black Things, very wicked Men, when sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported by other Presumptions, must be credited, since such Persons are the only proper Tools to be imployed on such occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sions. It is true, it was not proved, that any in Sir <hi>John Fen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wick</hi>'s
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:60872:15"/> Name had practised on him to go out of the way: But a Practice of corrupting <hi>Porter</hi> to go out of the way had been fully proved; in which Lady <hi>Mary Fenwick,</hi> and Sir <hi>John</hi>'s <hi>Sollicitor,</hi> had been concerned; which gave a strong Presump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion against him, and a just cause of Suspicion, that he was also concerned in the withdrawing the other Witness: But that was only a Suspicion.</p>
            <p>Another Practice that was proved to be carried on to discredit his Evidence was also brought as a Presumption; but that gave only occasion to another Suspicion as to the with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawing of <hi>Goodman:</hi> So the Business of <hi>Goodman</hi> was little insisted on.</p>
            <p>Another Matter was more urged; when Sir <hi>John</hi> was first taken, he writ a Letter to his Lady (which was taken from the Person to whom the conveying it was committed); in it, besides many other Directions, (by all which it appeared he looked on his own Case as desperate) he advised her to try, by Money, to gain some of the Jury, to <hi>starve the rest;</hi> and added, <hi>that or nothing must save my Life.</hi> This was then brought to the <hi>Lords Justices,</hi> (as was testified at the Bar of the House of Lords): And upon his first Examination before them, in which he denied every thing, they told him he was not of that Mind when he writ that Letter, which was then shewed him; to which he said nothing, but laid it down, and was silenced by it: That was considered as an implicit confessing of it.</p>
            <p>Some thought to have taken off this, by saying it was like the proceeding in Col. <hi>Sidney</hi>'s Case, upon the Similitude of Hands; but the barbarousness of that Case was, that a Book found lying in a Man's Study, writ many Years before, was brought to supply the want of a Second Witness, of a Treason of a few Months standing. It could not have been denied, but that if there had been Witnesses against <hi>Sidney,</hi> tho doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Ones, it was a violent Presumption to support their Credit; If it appeared by a Book of his own writing that he thought Kings might lawfully be put to Death. This was not urged
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:60872:15"/> as an Evidence but as a violent Presumption, that Sir <hi>John</hi> knew himself Guilty, and such certainly it was. But as <hi>Sidney</hi>'s Case was urged, so the Lord <hi>Russell</hi>'s Case was also insisted upon, which had been ever thought hard that upon some transient Discourses he had been condemned, and it was alledged that these were only Discourses at a <hi>Tavern;</hi> But there was a vast Difference between the <hi>one</hi> and the <hi>other.</hi> In the L. <hi>Russel</hi>'s <hi>Case</hi> there were only Discourses of the feasibleness of Seizing the <hi>Guards,</hi> but nothing was resolved on: And not one word was sworn to have been spoken by him. Whereas, here, a Messen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger was agreed on, a Messenger was sent to invite over a <hi>French Army;</hi> which were plainly <hi>Over't Acts.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The last thing</hi> I shall take notice of is, the Delay used by Sir <hi>John,</hi> after his Apprehension; According to the Contents of the Letter to my Lady <hi>Mary</hi> (which was talk'd of in <hi>Kent</hi> soon after 'twas written), very Sedulous Endeavours were used to have his <hi>Tryal</hi> postpon'd; That seem'd to be upon some Design, which he trusted to more then his Innocence. <hi>Goodman</hi> having been Apprehended, and Evidence having been given by him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst Sir <hi>John Fenwick</hi> before a <hi>Justice of Peace,</hi> the <hi>Grand Jury,</hi> and <hi>Petty Jury,</hi> upon the Tryal of Mr. <hi>Peter Cooke,</hi> who was Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned upon that Evidence: They saw that what was suffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to Convict Mr. <hi>Cooke</hi> was sufficient to Convict Sir <hi>John;</hi> the Evidence being as strong against the one as the other.</p>
            <p>Now what Course could be taken? One was a Pretence to make a Discovery, and to get time by sending a Letter over Sea to the King; in which ('tis said) he informed against se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral, both Lords and Commons, only upon <hi>Hear-say:</hi> In the mean while saying little that, after the Act of Grace, could touch his own Party, tho it might be presumed he knew more of them then others.</p>
            <p>Another Artifice (and which all this Train seemed to lead to) was to prevail with <hi>one</hi> of the <hi>Witnesses</hi> to withdraw. <hi>Porter</hi> was first tryed; but he was not to be dealt with (as they perceiv'd): No Money would buy him off, nor was he to be wheedled, or frighted.</p>
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:60872:16"/>
            <p>But at length, by some Means (and what they were, we may guess by their Attempt upon <hi>Porter); Goodman</hi> went out of the way.</p>
            <p>Which being effected, Sir <hi>John</hi> was safe (since the late Act requires two present Witnesses) <hi>for without a Bill of Attainder it was impossible he could fall under the Sentence of Death,</hi> as he sayeth in his <hi>Last Paper.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This was a more effectual Course then to get <hi>Two or Three who could starve the rest of the Jury:</hi> So he gives Direction in his Letter to my Lady <hi>Mary,</hi> if my Memory does not extream<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly fail me; adding, <hi>That or nothing can save me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This, Sir <hi>John</hi> depended so much upon, that, upon <hi>Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi>'s Absconding, he let fall his Pretences of making a Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery for the present.</p>
            <p>But this Bill having passed the Commons, was brought up to the Lords; where after a full and long Debate, and before the <hi>Third Reading,</hi> Sir <hi>John</hi> was askt what he had to say; he desired (as I was informed) <hi>three Things.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. That (according to what had been at first promised by the Lords) what He should say in that Court might not be made use of against him in any Inferiour Court; and also that he might have an Assurance of it from the <hi>King</hi> (for so he all-along called him, tho the Paper-writer gives Him no other Title then <hi>Prince of Orange.</hi>)</p>
            <p n="2">2. That he might have a <hi>Pardon</hi> before he Confessed.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That he might not be made use of as an <hi>Evidence</hi> after it.</p>
            <p>The King was Petitioned by the Lords for the <hi>First,</hi> and it was granted.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Second</hi> (it seems) was thought unreasonable; but yet (as I have heard) so far complyed with, that he was told, If he made such a Confession as would be satisfactory to that House, they would therein also intercede with the King; and bid him rest assured that they did not then doubt of the King's Favour, as to both the Last.</p>
            <p>But he did not think himself Secure, as he said, and so the Bill passed.</p>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:60872:16"/>
            <p>Thus I have given you, in as few Words as I could, the summe of this long Evidence: What remains but to consider the <hi>Circumstances</hi> relating to it, so far as I was enabled to learn.</p>
            <p>One main part of which was a Petition delivered by the Lords, at the Lady <hi>Mary</hi>'s Request to the King, for a Suspension of the Execution for <hi>eight Days,</hi> to which the Narrative was annexed, signifying that when time was he had saved the King's Life; and besides it was alledged that he wanted the Assistance of a Divine. The Former was of no force, for this Act (which he now challengeth to himself the benefit of) was a Year be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the last intended Assassination, and the Assassines were such as he freely and intimately Conversed with afterward; and yet he gave no Notice of it to the King nor to any one else that I could hear of; which if he had, Sir <hi>John</hi> would most certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly have made use of this Pretence in the Paper delivered to the Lords, and at his Death have justified himself upon it. The Neglect of which before, and the Omission of it afterwards, gave too great reason to suspect that it might be with him as it was with <hi>Lowick</hi> and <hi>Rookwood, who abhorred the Fact,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Vid.</hi> Rookwood<hi>'s Tryal,</hi> pag. 52.</note> but thought themselves however obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, contrary even to their own Sense, <hi>to obey Orders;</hi> according to the Commission which <hi>Crossby</hi> assured them he saw Signed by King <hi>James</hi> at St. <hi>Germains,</hi> and was sent away for <hi>England</hi> before he came from thence.</p>
            <p>So <hi>Knightly abominated the Thing as much as any Man Living; yet under some honourable and fair Pretence became so far engaged, that by a mistaken Notion of Honour he thought he could not retreat without the Infamy of Cowardise;</hi> to use his own Words which were <hi>read in Court,</hi> when he came to be tryed.</p>
            <p>The latter Pretence is frivolous <hi>[That he had no Ministers,]</hi> for (I have been credibly informed) that he had first of all the offer made of any of the Clergy that had taken the Oaths; and among the Bishops, such as had dissented about the Bill of Attainder. And when that was not accepted, he had his choice of three or four Non-jurants; and by their Refusal had made it neces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sary to the Government to permit none at all, or the late Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shop
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:60872:17"/> of <hi>Peterborough</hi> only; since the others that were Non-jurants refused to attend him, upon pretence that they might have the Oaths tendred them, and so stand convicted: A Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence that Dr. <hi>White</hi> and all the Non-jurants were alike liable to: But surely when they might have had leave from the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment to go, they might as well rely on the Justice and Honour of the Government as live under the Protection of it.</p>
            <p>I come now to the last part, which I promised, which is to make some <hi>Reflections</hi> upon the <hi>Paper</hi> which he delivered to the <hi>Sheriff.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Of what stamp this writing is we may easily judg. The Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tificial Contrivance of it, the little Avoidances, and Cautions stuck in every where, shew that they are not the words of one that had <hi>no Talent in writing,</hi> nor the free and undisguised thoughts of one that was immediately to dye. He professes to dye in the Communion of the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England;</hi> but whether this Paper be consistent with the Simplicity and Candour taught and required by that Church, especially in our last Hours, let the <hi>Reader</hi> judg.</p>
            <p>It doth not mightily concern the World to know what Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion Sir <hi>John Fenwick</hi> was of. I know no Perswasion over zealous to challenge him as theirs. I fear he was rather of a <hi>Party</hi> than of a <hi>Religion;</hi> and that was the Cause he died in. I acknowledg there was a Design of a Party to have made him a <hi>Martyr,</hi> as they had contrived it: If the Second Petition offer'd to the Lords had been received without Alterations, and when presented to the King, had been entirely complied with. If he had been respited for eight Days, according to the Petition, he had then suffered on the 30th of <hi>January,</hi> the <hi>Anniversary</hi> of a Noted <hi>Martyr</hi> of Blessed Memory; with whom he was not fit to be so much as <hi>named the same Day.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He saith, <hi>My Religion taught me my Loyalty, which, I bless God, is untainted: And I have ever endeavoured, in the Station wherein I have been placed, to the utmost of my Power, to support the Crown of</hi> England <hi>in the True and Lineal Course of Descent without Interruption.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:60872:17"/>
            <p>Now I would know what is meant by the <hi>True and Lineal Course of Descent?</hi> If he means thereby the next in Blood with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any Interruption, where is this always to be found? not in our <hi>Histories,</hi> nor in our <hi>Laws. Edward</hi> the <hi>Confessor</hi> (whose <hi>Cross</hi> was some years since so much reverenced by the late King, and who himself was esteemed a Guardian Saint) broke that <hi>Lineal Descent</hi> both in <hi>taking</hi> the Crown and <hi>leaving</hi> it at his Death; and whatever is due to the <hi>Blood,</hi> was never thought <hi>absolutely</hi> due to the <hi>Person,</hi> nor to the next in this <hi>Lineal Course of Descent.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Neither our Religion nor our Law teaches such a kind of Loyalty. It is not our Religion but the Law that determines our Loyalty as to the particulars of it; and so far, such as our Law determines our Loyalty to be, such doth our Religion determine it. Now what Law is there to keep a Prince by violence from leaving his People? That requires us to support the Crown on him, that will hold it upon no other Terms, than that his Will and Pleasure may be above it? What Law that obliges us to adhere to and assist <hi>Him,</hi> that, contrary to our Oaths of Allegiance and Supremacy, as well as those at his own Coronation, will Subjugate his People to a Forreign Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late or Potentate? And that would put himself wholly in the Power of such a Prince, whom above all in the World his People had no reason to expect Favour from? I know no such Law, nor any such Church of <hi>England</hi> that teaches such Loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alty, in any of those Books that are the Standard of it. And yet this is the Loyalty he (as he professes) dies <hi>Innocently</hi> for, and which he endeavoured to the <hi>utmost of his Power to support.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But farther, who is concerned in this <hi>True and Lineal Course of Descents?</hi> it is, in his opinion, the pretended <hi>Prince of Wales;</hi> whom he prays for in the Conclusion, and of whom he saith, <hi>it is impossible the Nation should prosper, till the Government is settled upon this right Foot.</hi> A Pretence which their way of Proof made at the best very doubtful. And we know, who once said it, that <hi>in dubiis melior est conditio possidentis.</hi> Certainly we shall be upon a very wrong Foot if we depart from the <hi>Act of Settlement.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:60872:18"/>
            <p>He goes on, <hi>As for what I am now to dye, I call God to witness, I went not to that Meeting in</hi> Leadenhall-street <hi>with any such intention, as to invite King</hi> James <hi>by Force to invade this Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; nor was I my self provided with either Horse or Arms, or enga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged for any number of Men, or gave a particular Consent for any such Invasion, as is most falsely Sworn against me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But what is become of the other Meeting at Mrs. <hi>Montjoy</hi>'s? that's perfectly dropp'd. And as for this at <hi>Leadenhall-street,</hi> that he cannot deny; nor doth he venture to call that part of the Evidence in question, which speaks to the Time or Persons, or the Matter then discoursed upon.</p>
            <p>But what hath he then to say? He came not thither <hi>with any intention to invite King</hi> James <hi>by Force to invade this Nation.</hi> Was this sworn against him? It was not the <hi>intention</hi> before hand, but the Subject matter of the Discourse that was proved upon him; if there was nothing of that Kind, no Design for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, no Message nor Messenger sent to invite King <hi>James,</hi> that is as soon denied as the <hi>Intention.</hi> But of that nor a word.</p>
            <p>But, however, he betakes himself to another Shift, <hi>viz. He was not himself provided with either Horse or Arms, or enga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged for any number of Men.</hi> A very doubtful way of Expression. <hi>He was not himself provided;</hi> but what need was there of a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent Provision, when the Service was to beat some Months di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance? or what if he was <hi>not himself provided,</hi> if it was to be provided for him? What need of any such Provision, when (as it was confessed) they were upon the Instant to seize Horse and Arms when occasion should be. And so it was formerly in the <hi>Gunpowder-Treason.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He saith, he was <hi>not engaged for any number of Men:</hi> but was he not one of those that were to raise 2000 Men in the gross, and it was not necessary the <hi>Quota</hi> of each particular Person should at that Meeting be set out.</p>
            <p>He goes on, <hi>Nor did I give particular Consent for any such In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vasion;</hi> that is not so charg'd upon him. All rose up and said to <hi>Charnock, Yes you may.</hi> Whether it was general, or whether it was a <hi>particular Consent,</hi> is not the Point. The <hi>Consent</hi> it
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:60872:18"/> seems is not denyed; And then where the Perjury is we are yet to seek.</p>
            <p>He proceeds, and <hi>I do also declare, in the presence of God, That I knew nothing of</hi> King James's <hi>coming to</hi> Calais, <hi>nor of any In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vasion intended from thence, till it was publickly known: And the only Notion I had that something might be attempted, was from the</hi> Thoulon <hi>Fleet coming to</hi> Brest.</p>
            <p>If this is true, it is evident the English were trusted with no more of the Secret than was absolutely necessary. It was found fit that the <hi>Assassination</hi> should lye upon them; it was a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sperate piece of Service, and if those forlorn Wretches perish in it, let them perish.</p>
            <p>But as to the Invasion, the <hi>when,</hi> and the <hi>whence,</hi> it was lodged with others, to whom the Profits and Advantages of a Conquest were reserved. It was sufficent that when these Conspirators heard the <hi>Thoulon Fleet was come to Brest,</hi> then upon this <hi>Signal,</hi> they were to be in readiness, and with the <hi>Horse</hi> they <hi>had</hi> or could <hi>seize,</hi> were to make their way as they could to the Coast, when they heard their Friends were land<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. This, it seems, was the <hi>only Notion</hi> Sir <hi>John</hi> and the rest (I suppose with him) had of the Invasion; and he saith, he knew it not till it was <hi>publick.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Information he gave, he is willing to make the best of in the next Paragraph; for, saith he, <hi>I also call God to witness that I receiv'd the knowledg of what is contein'd in those Papers, that I gave to a great Man that came to me in the</hi> Tower, <hi>both from Letters and Messages that came from</hi> France; <hi>and he told me when I read them to him, that the Prince of</hi> Orange <hi>had been acquainted with most of those things before.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This was what he himself did not believe when he talk'd of it long before (as one has affirm'd), but yet was pleased with it, because it <hi>would create Suspicions</hi> and <hi>Jealousies.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He acquaints us with another part of the <hi>Secret,</hi> that the <hi>Great Man,</hi> to whom he imparted it, could tell him the <hi>Prince of</hi> Orange <hi>had been acquainted with the most of this before.</hi> But what was it? Not that the <hi>Great Man</hi> knew of these <hi>Lords</hi> and
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:60872:19"/>
               <hi>Commons</hi> he accused, but of an Intelligence in general that passed between <hi>England</hi> and <hi>France.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As for his Expectation of Mercy from that Prince whose Life he pretended to have sav'd, it has been already consider'd.</p>
            <p>He goes on, as he began, with a profession of his Innocence, the accusing others of seeking his Blood, and charging the guilt of it upon the whole Nation; for saith he, <hi>I beg of God to par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don those who with great Zeal have sought my Life, and brought the Guilt of my Innocent Blood upon this Nation; no Treason be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing proved upon me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Other Malefactors may as well accuse the Judges and Juries, and Courts of Justice for seeking their Life, when they are Convicted, Condemned, and to be Executed for their Crimes: But why doth he thus arraign those that were concern'd in the Bill? Was he indeed Innocent? Was no Treason proved upon him? This he saith, and saith it when he comes to die. And yet if we believe, not the Evidence of others only, but himself, it is plainly otherwise. What was the meaning of his Confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion in his Letter to his Lady?</p>
            <p>What becomes of his Privity to the first Design <hi>of the Assassi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation</hi> which he did not discover? What of his Offers to confess again and again? What of his owning the Meeting, the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sign, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> How then is he Innocent? No, saith he, <hi>no Treason be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing prov'd upon me.</hi> Was there no Treason in inviting a Forreign Force? no Treason in joyning with it? no Treason in holding a Correspondence with the greatest Enemies of the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and Nation? The matter of Fact was too plain to be denied? And it was of that Nature which in the ordinary con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struction of the Law is Treason.</p>
            <p>Here then was Guilt, here was Treason. And how then can there be <hi>Innocent Blood,</hi> and of that Malignity as to lie upon the Nation?</p>
            <p>It must wholly rest then upon the Proof; <hi>No Treason being proved upon me.</hi> So that let the Malefactor be never so guilty, he may protest his Innocence, and charge the Guilt of <hi>Innocent Blood upon the Nation,</hi> if it is not in every Punctilio <hi>proved
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:60872:19"/> upon him.</hi> And yet this is all his Innocence is supported upon, as appears by what follows, <hi>viz. I return my most hearty Thanks to those Noble and Worthy Persons who gave me their Assistance, by opposing this Bill of Attainder; without which it had been im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>possible I could have fallen under the Sentence of Death.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Why Imposible? Might he not expect as much Justice from both Houses of Parliament, as from the Ministers of Justice, and the Juries, in the Inferiour Courts? Had he not the Privilege of being heard by his Counsel, and the Favour of all that could be said in his behalf by those <hi>Noble and Worthy Persons</hi> that in both Houses were against the Bill? Was he not himself heard and re-heard to the very utmost, and had all the Advantages al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed that one that stood thus accused could, and more then he could reasonably, expect? Why was it then <hi>Impossible?</hi> The reason is evident, because the other Witness was withdrawn; and according to the late Act, one, in the ordinary Course of Law being not sufficient, how clear soever the proof otherwise was; therefore without the Bill of Attainder it was <hi>Impossible.</hi> And thus we see at last upon what point his profession of Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency turns, and that he dies with the charge of the guilt of his <hi>Innocent Blood upon the Nation;</hi> and that is, because of the <hi>Attainder:</hi> and then all <hi>Attainders</hi> must be condemned; and if so, he is Innocent; but if that Course of Law is to be justified, as surely it is, (and has been before shewed) then he is guilty, and the Treason clearly and sufficiently <hi>proved upon him.</hi> So that upon the Whole, there is little else then Reservation and Equivocation; the Defence of which we leave to another Church, for that belongs not to the Church he professes to dye a Member of.</p>
            <p>If we were to construe his words (if his they were, otherwise then he made them such by his owning of them) according to the Contrivance of the rest, which are so full of Ambiguity and abstruse and doubtful Meaning; those <hi>Noble and Worthy Persons</hi> who have his Thanks, are no more beholding to him, then the others he Charges with seeking his Life, when he saith of them, I am fully satisfied <hi>they pleaded their own Cause when they
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:60872:20"/> pleaded mine.</hi> But what ever he meant, those <hi>Noble and Worthy</hi> Persons have given too great Assurances of being otherwise in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clined, to have any thing of that Nature made use of to their Disadvantage.</p>
            <p>He concludes with a Prayer; but it is too, a fixing upon him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self the Fact he stood charged with and died for; it is for the Abdicated King, and the Spurious Prince; that is, for the main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining of that Cause, which, he saith, he <hi>endeavoured to his utmost Power to promote.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Upon the Whole, it appears by his and his Friends Conduct, as well as by his Treasonable Practises, he had made it neces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sary to the Government to let the Sentence take effect. It was the Clemency of the Government that has emboldned the Enemies of it to proceed the more confidently in these Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctises; and at length to conclude, that because it <hi>did not,</hi> that it therefore <hi>durst not punish them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I know not how to conclude better then in the Words of Parlaiment, in their Late <hi>Act for better Security of His Majesty's Royal Person and Government;</hi> it saith, <hi>They have been delivered from the Bloody and Barbarous Attempts of Traitors and others His Majesty's Enemies, who, there is just reason to believe, have been in great measure encouraged, to Ʋndertake and Prosecute such, their wicked Designs, partly by His Majesty's great and undeserved Clemency towards them, and partly by want of a sufficient Provision in the Law for the securing Offices and Places of Trust to such as are well affected to His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iesty's Government, and for the repressing and punishing such as are known to be disaffected to the same.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>The End.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>